all right
[Music]
mindfulness is now a billion dollar
industry with as many as one in five
Fortune 500 companies implementing some
kind of workplace mindfulness programs
it has been rebranded
from hippie to be nonsense to portrayal
such as brain training
said to sell it better
these reductionist commodified forms
have been derided as Mick mindfulness
but who cares what they call it if it
works but does it Research into
mindfulness has been Complicated by the
fact that the term can mean anything
from informal practices such as
conscious awareness while eating to
structured meditation programs involving
designated specific times to sit in a
specific posture or attending to your
breathing for example this has made an
understanding of the efficacy hard to
capture can't hurt though right well
there have been more than 20
observational studies or case reports
documenting instances of adverse effects
such as meditation-induced psychosis
Mania anxiety panic in one perspective
study of an intensive meditation
Retreats 60 percent reported at least
one adverse effect including one
individual who was hospitalized for a
psychotic break even outside of an
immersive Retreat environment as many as
12 percent of meditators were called
serious negative side effects within 10
days of initiating the practice
it's considered plausible that adverse
effects occur at rates approximating
that of Psychotherapy with about 1 in 20
reporting lasting negative effects of
psychological treatment with about 18
million Americans practicing meditation
and as many as a million new meditators
a year even a five percent adverse event
rate could mean hundreds of thousands of
negative side effects a year as with any
medical intervention though it's all
about risks versus benefits
unfortunately many of the benefits
appear to have been overstated this
commentary in the Journal of the
American Psychological Association notes
that even the books on mindfulness
written by scientists are bursting with
magical Promises of peace happiness and
well-being
contrary to the popular perception the
evidence for even the most well-founded
benefits are not entirely conclusive
this is not an issue unique to
meditation of course there's a
replication crisis across the entire
field of experimental psychology where
many of the landmark findings in the
social sciences published in even the
most prestigious journals don't appear
to be reproducible
drug companies aren't the only ones to
suppress the publication of studies that
don't come out the way they want it the
majority of mindfulness-based Trials
apparently never see the light of day
raising the Specter of a similar
publication bias presumably if the study
showed promising results they would have
been released rather than shelved and
even many of the ones that do make it
into the scientific record are
underwhelming the federal Agency for
Health Care research and quality
published a systematic review of the
available data and conclude that
mindfulness meditation worked best for
improving anxiety depression and pain
but even then the quality of evidence
was only moderate what about weight loss
mindfulness-based modalities can help
with Stress Management self-control and
decreased impulsive eating as well as
binge eating and emotional eating all of
which might facilitate weight management
however systematic review of The
Evidence published about five years ago
failed to find evidence of signifi or
consistent weight loss part of the
problem is compliance like any other
diet or lifestyle intervention
mindfulness only works if you do it for
example randomized women to attend four
two-hour workshops that teach
mindfulness techniques such as cognitive
diffusion and after six months they lost
no more weight on average than the
control group however if you exclude
those who reported never applying the
workshop principles at all and just look
at those who at least use them some of
the time their weight loss did beat out
the control group by about five pounds
other Studies have shown a lack of
weight gain rather than loss for example
this study found that obese subjects in
the control group continued to gain
weight at about a pound a month whereas
the weight of those in the mindfulness
intervention group remains stable put
all the studies together in the latest
and largest review published did find
mindfulness-based interventions could
lead to weight loss compared to doing
nothing an average of about seven pounds
over around four months pitted Head to
Head they didn't beat out other
lifestyle change interventions but the
nice thing about Stress Management
mindfulness is they can be practiced on
top of whatever else you're doing
[Music]
thank you